Guide to the Ira and Edita Morirs Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Ira and Edita Morirs Papers,
1892-1988
Morris, Ira & Edita.
30.1 linear ft. (52 document boxes; 2 Flat Boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
MS#0904
5420146
Biographical Note
The authors Ira V. Morris and Edita (deToll) Morris married in February 1925. The son of Ira Nelson and Constance Lily (Rothschild) Morris, Ira V. Morris (1903-1972) was born in Chicago, Illinois. His father was a diplomat and he was raised abroad before earning a B. A. from Harvard University. During his literary career, Ira's fiction and non-fiction works often depicted the intrigues of Americans abroad and political subjects. Born in Orebro, Sweden, Edita deToll Morris (1902-1988) began her career writing short stories. Edita's first literary works were inspired by her childhood and then her writing expanded to reflect her travels and political interests. Her most notable success was The Flowers of Hiroshima, a novel about post-WWII Japan that earned international acclaim. In 1957, the couple founded Hiroshima House, a recreation center and hostel for the survivors of the atomic bombings. In addition, the Morris's were political activists committed to nuclear disarmament, opposed to many U.S. policies of the Cold War, and related causes. Edwin Seaver (1900- ), an American author and critic, was born in Washington, D. C. During his career, Edwin worked for the publisher Little, Brown, the Book of the Month Club, several magazines, and various newspapers. He edited short stories by Edita Morris for publication in Cross Section and other collections. It appears that Edwin had a relationship with Edita Morris following the deaths of their spouses.
Scope and Content
Manuscripts, correspondence, photographs, documents, printed materials, books, and other papers of Ira V. and Edita Morris from 1892 to 1988. The couple's literary careers are documented by typescripts, notes, book reviews, and published versions of their work. Some of these materials are written in French, German, Swedish, Japanese, and other foreign languages. Included are subject files, financial records, and materials related to the Hiroshima House for atomic bombing victims and the couple's political activities. In addition, there is correspondence, documents, and photographs related to Edwin Seaver and his family.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 2 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Arranged Correspondence
Series III: Manuscripts
Series IV: Writings by Others
Series V: Subject Files
Series VI: Notebooks
Series VII: Address Books
Series VIII: Documents
Series IX: Photographs
Series X: Art
Series XI: Books
Subjects
Morris, Edita, 1902-; Morris, I. V. (Ira Victor), 1903-; Japan--Hiroshima-shi.; American literature--20th century.; American literature--Women authors.; World War, 1939-1945--Japan--Hiroshima-shi.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 2-47; 49-52. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Annalita M. Alexander Gift 1999 accn number.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  Correspondence sent to Ira V. and Edita Morris from editors and notable literary figures. Also includes correspondence to and from Edwin Seaver.
  - Boyle, Kay To Edita Morris, San Francisco, CA, 25 May 1973, (1p. (with envelope) a.l.s.,) (Box 1)
  - Boyle, Kay To Ira V. Morris, [v.p.], 1960-1972, (12 a.l.s., 2 a.l.) (Box 1)
    [Includes Kay Boyle's comments on Ira V. Morris's manuscripts]
  - Cousins, Norman To Edita Morris, New York, NY, 18 March 1966, (1p. t.l.s.,) (Box 1)
  - Cousins, Norman To Ira V. Morris, New York, NY, 29 March 1967, (1p. t.l.s.,) (Box 1)
  - Geismar, Maxwell To Ira V. and Edita Morris, Harrison, NY, 1970-1973, (3 (with envelopes) t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Komroff, Manuel To Ira V. Morris, New York, NY, 31 May 1970, (2p. (with envelope) t.l.s.,) (Box 1)
  - Komroff, Manuel To Harold Straus, New York, NY, 28 Nov 1960, (1p. t.l.s.,) (Box 1)
    [Marked as copy; discusses Ira V. Morris's novel The Paper Wall]
  - Morris, Ira V. To Mr. Friedenthal, Rozay-en-Brie, FR, [n.d.], (1p. a.p.c.s.,) (Box 1)
  - Nearing, Scott To Ira V. Morris, Harborside, Maine, 11 Oct. 1960, (2p. t.l.s.,) (Box 1)
  - Priestley, J. B. To Ira V. Morris, Stratford-on-Avon, UK, 1 Dec. 1969, (2p. (with envelope) t.l.s.,) (Box 1)
  - Rosten, Norman To Edwin Seaver and Edita Morris, [v.p.], 1983-1986, (7 a.l.s., 19 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
    [Includes magazine clippings]
  - Seaver, Edwin To Edita Morris, New York, NY, 2 Nov. 1970 & 1 Aug. 1974, (2 t.l.s.,) (Box 1)
  - Styron, William To Ira V. Morris, Roxbury, CT, 27 Feb. 1968, (1p. (with envelope) a.l.s.,) (Box 1)
- Series II: Arranged Correspondence
  - Subseries II.1: Correspondence to and from the Morris's
    Correspondence to and from the Morris’s about their writing careers, Hiroshima Rest House Foundation, relationships, political activities, financial affairs, and other matters. Arranged alphabetically by last name of sender.
    - A, 1961-1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Abe, Tomoji, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Ambassade de la Republique Populaire de Chine, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Anand, Mulk Raj, 1965-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Arnoni, M. S. 1970, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - B, 1942-1972, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Baddeley, Hermione 1967-1968, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Barr, Anthony 1973 & 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Battle, Hyman, L. 1964-1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Beuscart, Abbé Albert 1937-1955 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Bradley, William A. 1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Buck, Pearl S. 1961 & 1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      [form letters]
    - Buckingham, Sue 1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Butler, William J. 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - C, 1957-1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Caine, Joy 1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Cameron, Angus 1959 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Chatto and Windus Ltd. 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - The Chinese People's Association for Friendship with Foreign Countries, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Collier, John, 1968-1970, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Cowasjee, Saros, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Curtis Brown, Ltd. 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - D, 1965-1984 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Davis-Poynter, R. G. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Dennis Dobson Publishers, 1965-1972 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Department of State, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Dunham, Barrows, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - E, 1965-1975, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Elias, George 1965, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - F, 1956-1965 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Faure, Edgar 1969 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Fifield, William 1965 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - First National Bank of Chicago, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Forest, Jean Kurt 1966 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - G, 1956-1981, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Galan, Victor Rico, 14 January 1970 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - George Braziller, Inc. 1971 & 1976 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - H, 1943-1976, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Hamai, Shinzo 1961-1966 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Hecht, Brayer & Grill, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Hinshaw, Milton L. 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Huberman, Leo 1966 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - I, 1965-1970 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - J, 1959-1970, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - K, 1957-1972, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Karl Pfankuch, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - L, 1961-1969, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Leeston, Osyth 1968 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Leresche, Hope 1965-1972 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Liepman, Ruth 1965 & 1985 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - M, 1965-1971, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Melville, Alan 1968 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Merriam, Eva, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Milton Academy, 1968 & 1970 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Mitani, E. 1960-1966 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Monthly Review Press, 1966-1971 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Mori, Koji, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Morito, Tatsuo, May [1960] (Box 3, Folder 58)
      [Printed thank you letter with calligraphy for the condolence wishes on the death of Mrs. Kishiko Morito from her husband, Showa 35]
    - Morris, Ivan, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Morris, Lloyd, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Myrdal, Gunnar 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - N, 1956-1976 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - National Guardian, 1961-1968 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - O, 1959-1970, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Olgin, Constantine 1959-1970, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Olgin, Louise 1959-1966, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Oppenheimer, Ernest K. 1960 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Osten, Suzanne 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Otto, Werner 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - P, 1952-1982, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Papandreou, Andréas 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Paradowski, Jan 1955-1961 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Pollinger, Murray 1972, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Porter, Russell 1965-1985 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Price, Stanley 1968 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Priestley, J. B. 1969 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - R, 1944-1970 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Rae, Douglas 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Redbook Magazine, 1963 & 1965 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Riley, B. 1971 (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Rothschild & Salwen, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - S, 1943-1985 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Scherman, Bernardine, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Schwartz, Robert J. 1965 & 1970 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Shohno, Naomi 1970 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Silva-Coronel, P. 1969 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Süddeutscher Verlag 1960-1973 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - T, 1943-1968, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Tamer, Ülkü 1970-1975 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Tanabe, Koichiro 1957-1965 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Tanabe, Koichiro 1966-1973 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Turney, Katherine 1968 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - U, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - V, 1959-1970 (Box 5, Folder 94)
    - W, 1965-1981 (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - Waugh, Alex 1960-1967 (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - Y, 1966-1973 (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Zimmeter, Wolf 1970 (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Unidentified fragments, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Unidentified, 1957-1959 (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Unidentified, 1960-1964 (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - Unidentified, Jan-June 1965 (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - Unidentified, July-Dec 1965 (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - Unidentified, 1966-1969 (Box 5, Folder 105)
    - Unidentified, 1970-1977 (Box 5, Folder 106)
    - Unidentified, 1982-1985 (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - Empty Envelopes, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 108)
    - Empty Envelopes, 1939-1959 (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - Empty Envelopes, 1960-1965 (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - Empty Envelopes, 1966-1969 (Box 6, Folder 111)
    - Empty Envelopes, 1970-1976 (Box 6, Folder 112)
    - Empty Envelopes, 1981-1986 (Box 6, Folder 113)
  - Subseries II.2: Correspondence by Others
    Correspondence involving neither Ira V. nor Edita Morris. Mainly correspondence sent to Edwin Seaver from colleagues and family members. Also includes 1892 letter to Lily Rothschild from Henry M. Wolf. Arranged alphabetically by last name of sender.
    - A, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - Backer, Ellen 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 115)
    - Bott, Dudley A. 1943-1944 (Box 6, Folder 116)
    - C, 1950-1968, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 117)
    - Cameron, Angus 1985, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 118)
    - Fifield, A. C. 1912 (Box 6, Folder 119)
    - H, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 120)
    - Iranyi, Helen 1984-1986 (Box 6, Folder 121)
    - M, 1981-1983, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 122)
    - Newhouse, Victoria 1985 (Box 6, Folder 123)
    - S, 1969 & 1974 (Box 6, Folder 124)
    - Seaver, Edwina 1983-1985 (Box 6, Folder 125)
    - Uphous, William 1960 (Box 6, Folder 126)
    - W, 1965-1973 (Box 6, Folder 127)
    - Wolf, Henry, 1892 (Box 6, Folder 128)
    - Unidentified, 1927-1993 (Box 6, Folder 129)
    - Empty Envelopes, 1975-1986 (Box 6, Folder 130)
- Series III: Manuscripts
  Drafts, notes, book reviews, published versions, and other materials related to manuscripts written by Ira V. and Edita Morris. It appears both authors edited each others work, therefore the handwritten corrections on drafts cannot be definitively identified.
  - Subseries III.1: Ira V. Morris
    Primarily drafts, typescripts, notes, fragments, and published versions of literary works by Ira V. Morris. Included are novels, short stories, essays, articles, speeches, and unpublished prose. In addition, there are book reviews, adaptations, and one scrapbook about his work. Arranged alphabetically by title, then chronologically.
    - "20 Years Later: The Hiroshima Bomb's Toll", article, published version appearing in National Guardian, 7 August 1965 (Box 6, Folder 131)
    - "Address for Mr. ______ Reception", speech, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 132)
    - "After the Bomb (21 Years After Hiroshima)", article, published version, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 133)
    - "Angers Talk", speech (2 versions), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 134)
    - "The Atom Bomb Comes of Age", speech, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 135)
    - "The Beautiful Fire", short story, complete draft, old (2 versions), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 136)
    - "The Beautiful Fire", short story, complete draft with handwritten corrections (3 versions), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 137)
    - "The Beautiful Fire", short story, complete draft, text in French (2 versions), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 138)
    - "The Beautiful Fire", short story, complete draft, last version, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 139)
    - "The Beautiful Fire", short story, fragments, text in French, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 140)
    - "Biographical Note", note (8 versions), 1967-1969, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 141)
    - "The Bombay Meeting", novel, incomplete draft, p. 1-14, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 142)
    - "The Bombay Meeting", novel, fragments, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 143)
    - "The Bombay Meeting", book reviews, 1955-1958 (Box 7, Folder 144)
    - "Les Bombes", article, published version, text in French, July 1970 (Box 7, Folder 145)
    - "The Bombs", essay, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 146)
      [Letter from Mervyn Jones to Ira V. Morris 23 July [n.y.] removed to Correspondence series, box 3, folder 44]
    - "La Borgia" (or "The Heirs"; or "Opposite the Metropolitan"), novel, final revision ready for printing, p.1-132, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 147)
    - "La Borgia" (or "The Heirs"; or "Opposite the Metropolitan"), novel, final revision ready for printing, p.133-253, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 148)
    - "La Borgia" (or "The Heirs"; or "Opposite the Metropolitan"), novel, fragments, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 149)
    - "La Borgia" (or "The Heirs"; or "Opposite the Metropolitan"), novel, corrections, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 150)
    - "La Borgia" (or "The Heirs"; or "Opposite the Metropolitan"), novel, critical comments, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 151)
    - "La Borgia" (or "The Heirs"; or "Opposite the Metropolitan"), novel, suggestions for revising, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 152)
    - "La Borgia" (or "The Heirs"; or "Opposite the Metropolitan"), novel, ultra-final notes, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 153)
    - "La Borgia", dramatic treatment (2 versions), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 154)
    - "La Borgia", blurb (3 versions), [1966?] (Box 7, Folder 155)
      [Letter from Ira V. Morris to Mrs. Norah Smallwood, 8 Dec. 1966 removed to Correspondence series, box 2, folder 18]
    - "La Borgia", novel, printed version, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 156)
    - "La Borgia", book reviews, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 157)
    - "La Borgia", film project, 1970-1972, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 158)
    - "The Chicago Story", scrapbook with clippings of book reviews, 1952-1954 (Box 8, Folder 159)
    - "Clouds Over the Oases", essay (4 versions), n.d. (Box 8, Folder 160)
    - "The Deed", introduction, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 161)
    - "Experiment in the Punjab", article, complete draft (2 versions), n.d. (Box 8, Folder 162)
    - "Experiment in the Punjab", article, published version appearing in The Sunday Tribune, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 163)
    - "Experiment in the Punjab", article, published version appearing in The Times of Ceylon, 19 Feb. 1957 (Box 8, Folder 164)
    - "The Fall of Valor", essay, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 165)
    - "Formation of a French Anti-nuclear Warfare Organization", essay, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 166)
    - "A Great Noble Laureate", essay, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 167)
    - "The Greek Tragedy", letter to the editor of the New York Times, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 168)
    - "The Greek Tragedy", public letter, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 169)
    - "Hiroshima: 20 Years After", article, published version appearing in Le Nouvel Observator, text in French, 4 Aug. 1965 (Box 8, Folder 170)
    - "Hiroshima: 20 Years After", article, published version appearing in the New Statesman, 6 Aug. 1965 (Box 8, Folder 171)
    - "Hizoshima 1968: les suzvivants", article, [1968?] (Box 8, Folder 172)
    - "Icarus in Queens" (or "Sophocles in Queens"), short story, complete draft (3 versions), n.d. (Box 8, Folder 173)
    - "Icarus in Queens" (or "Sophocles in Queens"), short story, complete draft with handwritten corrections, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 174)
    - "Icarus in Queens" (or "Sophocles in Queens"), short story, fragments, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 175)
    - "Include Me Out", short story, complete draft (4 versions), n.d. (Box 8, Folder 176)
    - "Include Me Out", short story, complete draft with handwritten corrections, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 177)
    - "Include Me Out", short story, complete draft, ultra-final version, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 178)
    - "Include Me Out", short story, complete draft with handwritten corrections and comments, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 179)
    - "Include Me Out", short story, fragments, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 180)
    - "Interview with Miguel Angel Asturias", article, complete draft (2 versions), n.d. (Box 9, Folder 181)
    - "Interview with Miguel Angel Asturias", article, published version appearing in Le Revue de Paris, text in French, Feb. 1968 (Box 9, Folder 182)
    - "Interview with Miguel Angel Asturias", article, published version appearing in Monthly Review, March 1968 (Box 9, Folder 183)
    - "Jamaica in the Eagle's Shadow", article, complete draft (6 versions), [1967?] (Box 9, Folder 184)
      [Letter from Paul Johnson, the New Statesman, to Ira V. Morris, 7 March 1967 removed to Correspondence series, box 3, folder 62]
    - "Jamaica in the Eagle's Shadow", article, fragments, [1967?] (Box 9, Folder 185)
    - "Jamaica in the Eagle's Shadow", article, published version appearing in National Guardian, March 1967 (Box 9, Folder 186)
    - "Au Kenya, les colons sont les vrais Mau-Mau", article, published version appearing in L'Observateur, text in French, July 1953 (Box 9, Folder 187)
    - "The Kenya Terror", article, published version, June 1953 (Box 9, Folder 188)
    - "The Kidnapping" (or "The Hot Box"), novel, complete draft [#1], p.1-148, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 189)
    - "The Kidnapping" (or "The Hot Box"), novel, complete draft [#1], p.149-273, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 190)
    - "The Kidnapping" (or "The Hot Box"), novel, complete draft [#2], p.1-152, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 191)
    - "The Kidnapping" (or "The Hot Box"), novel, complete draft [#2], p.153-280, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 192)
    - "The Kidnapping" (or "The Hot Box"), novel, complete draft [#3], p.1-152, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 193)
    - "The Kidnapping" (or "The Hot Box"), novel, complete draft [#3], p.153-280, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 194)
    - "The Kidnapping" (or "The Hot Box"), novel, incomplete draft, p.1-49, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 195)
    - "The Kidnapping" (or "The Hot Box"), novel, incomplete draft, p.50-129, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 196)
    - "The Kidnapping" (or "The Hot Box"), novel, incomplete draft, p.130-212, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 197)
    - "The Kidnapping" (or "The Hot Box"), novel, fragments with handwritten corrections, p.1-100, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 198)
    - "The Kidnapping" (or "The Hot Box"), novel, fragments with handwritten corrections, p.119-279, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 199)
    - "The Kidnapping" (or "The Hot Box"), novel, fragments, p.1-100, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 200)
    - "The Kidnapping" (or "The Hot Box"), novel, fragments, p.101-217, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 201)
    - "The Kidnapping" (or "The Hot Box"), novel, handwritten notes, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 202)
    - "The Kidnapping" (or "The Hot Box"), novel, line changes, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 203)
    - "The Kidnapping", novel, agreement with Dobson Books Limited, 8 Aug. 1972 (Box 11, Folder 204)
    - "The Kimono", short story, complete draft (3 versions), n.d. (Box 11, Folder 205)
    - "The Kimono", short story, complete draft with handwritten corrections, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 206)
    - "The Kimono", short story, incomplete draft with handwritten corrections, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 207)
    - "The Kimono", short story, fragments, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 208)
    - "Letter from Hiroshima", article, complete draft (3 versions), n.d. (Box 11, Folder 209)
    - "Letter from Hiroshima", article, complete draft with handwritten corrections, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 210)
    - "Letter from Hiroshima", article, fragments, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 211)
    - "Love Letter", short story, complete draft (2 versions), [1940?] (Box 11, Folder 212)
    - "Love Letter", short story, published version, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 213)
    - "The Mau-Mau is a White Settler", essay, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 214)
    - "Message to Hiroshima Friends", speech, 6 Aug. 1971 (Box 11, Folder 215)
    - "Napalm Comes to America", article (2 versions), n.d. (Box 11, Folder 216)
    - "Mr. Nasashi Nii", speech, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 217)
    - "The Paper Wall", novel, title pages and table of contents, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 218)
    - "The Paper Wall", novel, answers to editors' quotes (2 versions), n.d. (Box 11, Folder 219)
    - "The Paper Wall", proposed blurb (6 versions), n.d. (Box 11, Folder 220)
    - "The Paper Wall", book reviews, 1959-1961 (Box 12, Folder 221)
    - "Paris Letter", essay, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 222)
    - "Project for a Series of Articles on the Peril of Growing Military Power", article, 1969, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 223)
    - "Repression in Mexico", letter, published version appearing in the Herald Tribune, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 224)
    - "The Road to Spain", novel, complete draft, p.1-180, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 225)
    - "The Road to Spain", novel, complete draft, p.181-426, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 226)
    - "The Road to Spain", novel, complete draft, p.427-525, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 227)
    - "The Road to Spain", novel, incomplete draft with handwritten corrections, p.1-206, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 228)
    - "The Road to Spain", novel, incomplete draft with handwritten corrections, p.207-376, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 229)
    - "The Road to Spain", novel, incomplete draft with handwritten corrections, p.377-525, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 230)
    - "The Road to Spain", novel, incomplete draft, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 231)
    - "The Road to Spain", novel, fragments, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 232)
    - "The Road to Spain", excerpt of letter from Carleton Beals (2 versions), n.d. (Box 13, Folder 233)
    - "The Road to Spain", book reviews, 1966-1967 (Box 13, Folder 234)
    - "Shifting Sands" (or "The Winds of Change"), novel, incomplete draft with handwritten corrections, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 235)
    - "Shifting Sands" (or "The Winds of Change"), novel, incomplete draft with handwritten corrections, copy #2, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 236)
    - "Shifting Sands" (or "The Winds of Change"), novel, discarded pages, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 237)
    - "Some Thoughts on the A-Bomb Survivors", essay, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 238)
    - "The Stockholm Novel" (or "The Stockholm Saga"), novel, incomplete draft with handwritten corrections (2 versions), n.d. (Box 13, Folder 239)
    - "The Stockholm Novel" (or "The Stockholm Saga"), novel, project notes, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 240)